Telesphor Insse Papers
Telesphor Insse Papers
1858-1868
Insse, Telesphor.
.25 linear ft.
Correspondence, financial documents, and miscellaneous items of the Canadian immigrant and Union soldier during the Civil War.
2664851
Biographical History
Telesphor Insse, a Civil War soldier, appears to have been a Canadian by birth who emigrated to the area of Canandaigua, New York, with members of his family. Two married sisters, one unmarried sister who worked, and three brothers all lived in the Canandaigua area. He was a painter by trade and lived in Bristol Center, New York. His brothers Boswell and Gregoire volunteered for service early in the Civil War, the former being discharged in 1863 because of wounds and the latter mustered out when his term of service was ended in 1863. Telesphor seems to have entered the Union army in 1862 and to have spent his term of service, which was with the 148th Regiment of New York State Volunteers, in the area of Norfolk and Portsmouth, Virginia. When released from service at the end of the war, he returned to the Canandaigua area.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Telesphor Insse Papers contain correspondence, financial documents, and miscellaneous items.
Virtually all the Correspondence, 1858-1865, consists of letters addressed to Telsephor Insse. The one exception is a letter dated February 9, 1862, to Boswell Insse from an uncle, William Burch, in Canada. One other letter lacks an identifiable addressee. About half of the letters were written by the soldier's relatives; the other half came from friends in the Canandaigua area. The letters from his brothers in the army contain a small amount of information regarding camp life and the Peninsular Campaign of General George B. McClellan in 1862, but are mostly personal in nature. The bulk of the correspondence deals with people and events in the Canandaigua area during the war. As such, it too is primarily personal in nature. A complete letter list and an alphabetical index of the correspondents are appended to this inventory.
The Financial documents date from 1861 and 1866-1868. A small account book details some of Telesphor Insse's employment as a painter after his return to civilian life. One folder of receipts shows materials purchased by Gregoire Insse.
The section of Miscellanea includes two folders of Civil War memorabilia: a handwritten day pass issued to Telesphor Insse for a visit to friends near his camp and three printed prayer cards, possibly intended for soldiers in the field. A set of painting instructions, apparently for the graining of wood, may be in Insse's hand. Two fliers for Horace Greeley's history of the Civil War, The American Conflict, for which Insse sought to be a sales agent, and the notice granting him the agency in his home town, complete the collection.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically, with a group of undated letters at the end. Financial documents and miscellanea are arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
has several collections relating to the Civil War. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Military history; New York State; Civil War (U.S.); Greeley, Horace, 1811-1872.; Insse, Telesphor -- Archives.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; Account books.; Correspondence.; Receipts (financial records); Military passes.; Soldiers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased as part of the Kohen Collection, circa 1964.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - [General], 1858-1865; 5 folders (Box 1)
  - [General], Undated (Box 1)
  - Envelopes (Box 1)
- Financial documents
  - Account book, 1866-1868 (Box 1)
  - Receipts, 1861 (Box 1)
- Miscellanea
  - Military pass for Telesphor Insse, 1862 (Box 1)
  - Notes on painters' supplies needed to stain or grain wood, undated; 2 items (Box 1)
  - Prayer cards, perhaps as printed for Civil War soldiers, pr. mat., undated; 3 items (Box 1)
  - Sales promotion material on Horace Greeley's The American Conflict and a printed form arranging an agency for Telesphor Insse to sell the book in Ontario County, N.Y., 1864; 1865; 2 items (Box 1)
Selected index to correspondence
[unidentified] Sep 7 1864
B—, Joseph and Elizabeth Oct 3 1858
Burch, Charity (co-signer) Feb 20 1859
Burch, Francis (co-signer) Feb 20 1859
Burch, William Feb 9 1862
Gardner, Amelia Jul 15 [no year]
Gardner, Harvey Nov 30 1862 Mar 2 1863 Apr 2 1863 May 3 1863 May 13 1863 Jun 3 1863 Jan 29 1865
Gilbert [?], Victoria Mar 9 [no year]
Goff, Isaiah L. Mar 1 1862
Goff, Martin Mar 1 1863 May 24 1863
Gooding, Ed[win] Mar 17 1863 Mar 29 1863 Jun 1 1863
Gregg, George Mar 9 1863 Apr 19 1863
Guinn [?], John M. Mar 1 1863
Hayes, Margaret (Insse) Nov 30 1862 Jul 9 1863
Hunn [?], Marcia A. Mar 13 1863
Insse, Boswell Jan 29 [no year] Apr 5 [no year] Apr 6 [no year] Feb 13 1862 May 11 1862
Insse, Francis Dec 24 1862 Mar 6 1863 Mar 22 1863 May 22 1863
Insse, Gregoire Oct 18 1861 Apr 27 1862 Mar 5 1863 Mar 21 1863 Jul 5 1863 Oct 9 1863
Insse, Helen M. Oct 24 1865
Insse, Margaret See Margaret Hayes